Guide to the Floyd Millard Riddick Papers, 1909-2000
Floyd Millard Riddick papers 1909-2000
Riddick, Floyd Millard, 1908-2000
43.3 Linear Feet 26,343 Items
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of Floyd Millard Riddick (1908-2000), U.S. Senate Parliamentarian 1964-1974 and author of books on parliamentary procedure, were donated to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library between 1977 and 1998. The papers span the years 1909-2006.
Biographical Note
1908, July 13 Born in Trotsville, NC
1931 Received BA from Duke University
1932 Received MA from Vanderbilt University
1935 Received PhD from Duke University
1936-1939 Taught Political Science at American University
1939-1943 Editor, Congressional Daily
1941 Published Congressional Procedure
1943-1947 Editor, Legislative Daily
1947 Established Daily Digest in Congressional Record
1947-1951 Senate editor for Daily Digest
1948 Published Congress in Action
1949 Published The U. S. Congress: Organization and Procedure
1951 Became Assistant Parliamentarian of the U.S. Senate
1958 Published Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices
1964 Became Parliamentarian of the U.S. Senate Published second edition of Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices
1974 Named Parliamentarian Emeritus at his retirement. Published third edition of Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices
1981 Published fourth edition of Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices
1992 Published fifth edition titled Riddick's Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices
2000 Died
Collection Overview
The Floyd Millard Riddick Papers, 1909 to 2000, (bulk 1950-1983), consist of correspondence, writings and speeches, printed material, senate documents, photographs, and organizational papers documenting Riddick's career as the Assistant Parliamentarian, Parliamentarian, and Parliamentarian Emeritus of the United States Senate. The Correspondence Series includes correspondence to and from senators, presidents, and other political figures concerning the rules and procedures of the United States Senate.
Between 1937 and 1947, some of the letters in the Correspondence Series relate to social conditions and political events in Germany before, during, and after World War II. Riddick, who resided in Germany during 1937 and 1938, maintained correspondence with friends and associates during this period. The letters provide insight into the ways in which the rise of National Socialism and the War affected this group of friends. Among the letters from Riddick's acquaintances in Germany is one giving an account of Krystallnacht; several from a young Jewish woman who wanted Riddick to assist her in obtaining admission to the United States as a student; and a few from a man who became a German soldier. A scrapbook and Riddick's personal diary (Miscellaneous Series) add further commentary on pre-war Germany.
Early in his senatorial career, Riddick was actively involved and interested in the organization and procedures guiding Congress. He began publishing books on parliamentary procedure in 1941, and by his retirement in 1974 he was honored for his dedication to congressional procedures and named Parliamentarian Emeritus. Considered to be the authority on parliamentary procedure, Riddick continues to edit and republish Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices. The Writings and Speeches Series consists primarily of notes, drafts, proofs, and copies of Riddick's published works and of notes for speeches made by Riddick. The Senate Activities Series contains material pertaining to Senate committees and task forces of which Riddick was a member. Agendas, pamphlets, and correspondence pertaining to other organizations of which Riddick was a member comprise the Organizational Records Series. This series includes papers relating to practicums on parliamentary issues held by Riddick for members of the American Institute of Parliamentarians.
Photographs of Riddick, his acquaintances, and his associates, many of whom were prominent political figures, make up the Picture Series. The Printed Material Series contains clippings, pamphlets, programs, and congressional documents pertaining to or of interest to Riddick. The Miscellaneous Papers Series includes an assortment of materials including awards Riddick received, documents relating to his trip to Germany, a diary (with transcription), scrapbooks kept by Riddick, and retirement tributes.
The addition (2007-0165) (50 items; 0.9 lin. ft.; 1928-2000) consists of Riddick's publications about parliamentary procedure; obituaries and other remembrances addressed to Riddick's wife upon his death; his high school diploma; and several VHS tapes, audiocassettes, and a mini-VHS cassette containing interviews and presentations by Riddick about his role as the Senate Parliamentarian.
The addition (2008-0179) (100 items; 0.6 lin. ft.; 1933-1992) contains publications, academic materials, clippings, correspondence, and miscellaneous materials, including a copy of the Senate Resolution 443 that declared Riddick to be the Parliamentarian Emeritus of the U.S. Senate. This addition has been interfiled with Accession (2007-0165).
The addition (2014-0073) (140 items; 0.2 lin. ft; 1937-2007) contains publications, biographical materials, clippings, correspondence, two print materials, photographs, and several miscellaneous drafs and documents. Publications include Riddick's descriptions of general Senate procedures and protocol,including those during impeachment. The bulk of the photographs, correspondence, and clippings are from the end of Riddick's life (1980-2000).
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
United States. Congress. Senate -- History.
United States. Congress. Senate -- Rules and practice
Legislators -- United States -- Correspondence
Jews -- Germany -- History -- 1933-1945.
Parliamentary practice -- United States.
Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945)
Crystal Night, 1938.
Germany -- History -- 1933-1945.
Germany -- Social life and customs -- 20th century.
Photographs
Riddick, Floyd Millard, 1908-2000
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1928-1997 and undated (bulk 1948-1983).
  Contains letters to and from Riddick. Much of the correspondence concerns Riddick's writings on senate procedure; questions of general parliamentary procedure; and speaking engagements. Many letters are from United States Senators and other political figures. Includes some correspondence between Riddick and his family, friends, and his students.
  Materials arranged chronologically by year. Greeting cards, many of which bear personal messages from political figures, are arranged chronologically at the end of the correspondence series, as are requests from Senate associates for editions of Riddick's Senate Procedures.
  - 1928-1941, (12 folders) (Box CS 1)
  - 1942-1948, (7 folders) (Box CS 2)
  - 1949-1956, (8 folders) (Box CS 3)
  - 1957-1964, (8 folders) (Box CS 4)
  - 1965-1969, (6 folders) (Box CS 5)
  - 1970-1974, (7 folders) (Box CS 6)
  - 1975-1977,March, (7 folders) (Box CS 7)
  - 1977, April-1979, (10 folders) (Box CS 8)
  - 1980-1982, September, (8 folders) (Box CS 9)
  - 1982, October-1985, (13 folders) (Box CS 10)
  - 1986-1989, (10 folders) (Box CS 11)
  - 1990-1997, (12 folders) (Box CS 12)
  - N.D., (1 folder)
  - Greeting Cards, 1938-1996and undated, (2 folders) (Box CS 13)
  - Invitations, 1954-1994 and undated, (1 folder)
  - Requests: Senate Procedures, 1981-1992, (2 folders)
- Senate Activities Series, 1947-1987, undated(bulk 1974-1985).
  Contains papers documenting Riddick's activities in the U.S. Senate, chiefly generated by Senate committees and pertaining to Riddick's responsibilities as Senate Parliamentarian. Some government publications are included in this series and are interfiled with papers relating to them.
  Items are arranged alphabetically by subject and are arranged chronologically by year within each subject.
  - Cloture Rule, undated, (1 folder) (Box SA 1)
  - Contested New Hampshire Election, 1974-1975, (2 folders)
  - Contested New Election: Open Session of the Committee on Rules and Administration Contesting the Election... New Hampshire, 1975, (2 volumes) (Box SA 2)
  - House and Senate Resolutions, 1971-1987, (1 folder)
  - Impeachment: Transcript of Proceedings: Committee on Rules and Administration... Impeachment, 1974, (4 volumes)
  - Impeachment: Transcript of Proceedings: Committee on Rules and Administration... Impeachment, 1974, (4 volumes) (Box SA 3)
  - Impeachment: Rules and Administration, 1974, (4 folders)
  - Impeachment: Senate Impeachment Committee, 1986, (1 folder)
  - Intelligence Activities, Establishment of Committee on, 1976, (5 folders) (Box SA 4)
  - Intelligence: Transcripts of Proceedings: Committee on Rules and Administration, 1976, (4 volumes) (Box SA 5)
  - Intelligence, Select Committee on, 1977, (1 folder)
  - Pearson-Ribicoff Study Group, 1983, (1 folder)
  - Practices and procedures, Study Group on Senate, 1983, (1 folder)
  - Reorganizing the Committee System of Senate,1977, (2 folders)
  - Reorganizing the Committee System of Senate,1976 and undated, (1 folder) (Box SA 6)
  - Reorganizing the Committee System of Senate,1977, (3 folders)
  - Reorganizing the Committee System of Senate: Open Markup Sessions: Committee System Reorganization Amendments,1977, (volume)
  - Reorganizing the Committee System of Senate: Hearings Before the Committee on Rules and Administration... Committee System Reorganization,1977, (volume)
  - Reorganizing the Committee System of the Senate:; Temporary Select Committee to Study the Senate Committee System, 1975-1976, (1 folder)
  - Reorganizing the Committee System of the Senate:; Temporary Select Committee to Study the Senate Committee System,1976, (2 folders) (Box SA 7)
  - Rules and Administration, Committee on, 1947-1977, (3 folders)
  - Rules and Administration, Committee on, 1978-1984and undated, (4 folders) (Box SA 8)
  - Rules and Administration, Committee on, Lists of Members from 1867 to 1990, (1 folder)
  - Standing Rules of the Senate and Congressional Budget and Impoundment Control Act of 1974, 1987, (volume) (Box SA 9)
  - Standing Rules of the Senate: Transcript of Proceedings: Subcommittee on Standing Rules of the Senate,1975, (volume)
  - Standing Rules of the Senate, 1975-1979, (5 folders)
  - Standing Rules of the Senate,1979, (6 folders) (Box SA 10)
  - Standing Rules of the Senate,1979, (9 folders) (Box SA 11)
  - Standing Rules of the Senate,1979 and undated, (6 folders) (Box SA 12)
  - Standing Rules of the United States Senate and Statutory provisions... Senate, 1979, (volume)
  - Miscellaneous, 1912-1978, June, (6 folders) (Box SA 13)
  - Miscellaneous, 1978, July -1987, undated, (7 folders) (Box SA 14)
  - Miscellaneous, undated, (2 folders) (Box SA 15)
  - Miscellaneous, Rule Amendment Proposals (1789-1943), undated, (2 volumes) (Box SA 16)
- Writings and Speeches, 1930-1992and undated(bulk 1964-1981).
  The Writings and Speeches series contains notes, articles, drafts, and published works by Riddick. Notable in this series are the working editions of Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices and the 1989and 1992editions entitled Riddick's Senate Procedure.
  Items are arranged alphabetically by title and then chronologically by year.
  - Articles: Typescripts, 1930, 1934-1966,June, (5 folders) (Box WS 1)
  - Articles: Typescripts, 1966, July-1989, undated, (5 folders) (Box WS 2)
  - Articles: Typescripts, undated, (5 folders) (Box WS 3)
  - Articles: Typescripts, undated, (1 folder) (Box WS 4)
  - Articles on Congress: Notes, undated, (2 folders)
  - Articles on Congress, 1939-1968, (volume)
  - Articles on Congress and Trade, 1968, (volume)
  - Senate Documents, 1975, (volume)
  - Triumvirate Rule in the House of Representatives from 1925-1931, 1932(Thesis volume)
  - Daily Digest Column for Congressional Record: 76th-83rd Congress, (5 folders) (Box WS 5)
  - Daily Digest Column for Congressional Record: 83rd -90th Congress, (8 folders) (Box WS 6)
  - The Classification of United States Senators, (1 folder) (Box WS 7)
  - The Classification of United States Senators, (volume)
  - History of the Committee on Rules and Administration draft, 1979, (2 folders)
  - History of the Committee on Rules and Administration, (volume)
  - Legislative Daily, 78th Congress, 1943-1944, (2 volumes)
  - Legislative Daily, 79th Congress, 1945-1946, (3 volumes) (Box WS 8)
  - Legislative Daily, 83rd Congress, 1953, (1 folder)
  - Legislative Outlook, Legislative Roundup, 1945-1946, (volume) (Box WS 9)
  - Local Government in Germany under the Third Reich, 1938, (1 folder)
  - Majority and Minority Leaders of the Senate,1969-1988editions, (5 folders containing pamphlets)
  - Notes: Congressional Record,undated, (2 folders) (Box WS 10)
  - Notes: Miscellaneous, undated, (4 folders)
  - Riddick's Rules of Procedure drafts and proofs, 1985, (5 folders, 2 volumes) (Box WS 11)
  - Riddick's Senate Procedure, 1989, (1 folder)
  - Riddick's Senate Procedure, Miscellaneous, 1989, undated, (1 folder) (Box WS 12)
  - Riddick's Senate Procedure, Draft, 1991, (5 folders)
  - Riddick's Senate Procedure, Backup disks, 1991, 21 May, (3 disks)
  - Riddick's Senate Procedure, Draft, 1991, (6 folders) (Box WS 13)
  - Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices Miscellaneous drafts, 1958, (Folders 1-8) (Box WS 14)
  - Senate Procedures: Precedents and Practices Miscellaneous drafts, 1958, (Folders 9-14) (Box WS 15)
  - Senate Procedures: Precedents and Practices Miscellaneous drafts, 1958, (Folders 15-20) (Box WS 16)
  - Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices, 1958, (2 volumes) (Box WS 17)
  - Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices Bound galley proofs, 1964, (3 volumes) (Box WS 18)
  - Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices Authorization to Print, 1972, (1 folder) (Box WS 19)
  - Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices Draft: A-Amendments, 1974, (5 folders)
  - Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices Draft: Amendments-Com, 1974, (6 folders) (Box WS 20)
  - Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices Draft: Conc-Deb, 1974, (6 folders) (Box WS 21)
  - Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices Draft: Deb-Gen, 1974, (5 folders) (Box WS 22)
  - Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices Draft: Gen-Quo, 1974, (6 folders) (Box WS 23)
  - Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices Draft: Rec-Sen, 1974, (5 folders) (Box WS 24)
  - Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices Draft: Sen-Vot, 1974, (5 folders) (Box WS 25)
  - Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices Draft: Vot-Wash, 1974, (2 folders) (Box WS 26)
  - Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices Draft: Index A-Y, 1974, (3 folders)
  - Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices Draft, 1974, (1 folder) (Box WS 27)
  - Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices Resource material, 1974, (2 folders)
  - Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices, 1974, (volume)
  - Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices Draft: Adj-Clo, 1981, (5 folders) (Box WS 28)
  - Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices Draft: Com-Cons, 1981, (5 folders) (Box WS 29)
  - Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices Draft: Consideration, 1981, (1 folder) (Box WS 30)
  - Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices Draft: Miscellaneous, 1981, (2 folders)
  - Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices Galley proofs, 1981, (1 folder)
  - Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices Proofs, 1981, (4 folders) (Box WS 31)
  - Senate Procedure: Precedents and Practices, 1981, (volume)
- Organizations Series, 1941-1997and undated
  Contains correspondence and printed material pertaining to organizations with which Riddick was involved. The bulk of this series contains materials pertaining to the American Institute of Parliamentarians.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of organization and chronologically within each folder.
  - American Institute of Parliamentarians, 1965-1981, (6 folders) (Box OS 1)
  - American Institute of Parliamentarians, 1982, (7 folders) (Box OS 2)
  - American Institute of Parliamentarians, 1983, (7 folders) (Box OS 3)
  - American Institute of Parliamentarians, 1984-1986, (8 folders) (Box OS 4)
  - American Institute of Parliamentarians, 1987-1990, (8 folders) (Box OS 5)
  - American Institute of Parliamentarians, Ethics Committee, 1988-1994., (1 folder)
  - American Institute of Parliamentarians, 1991-1993, (6 folders) (Box OS 6)
  - American Institute of Parliamentarians, 1994-1996, (3 folders) (Box OS 7)
  - American Institute of Parliamentarians, 1996, (1 volume)
  - American Institute of Parliamentarians, 1997, (1 folder)
  - American Institute of Parliamentarians, undated( 2 folders)
  - American Institute of Parliamentarians: Comments on Riddick's Practicum Lectures, undated( 1 folder)
  - American Institute of Parliamentarians:; Hearst Project, 1988-1989, (1 folder)
  - American Institute of Parliamentarians: Know Your Rights, 1992, (1 folder) (Box OS 8)
  - American Institute of Parliamentarians: Scrapbook of "The Floyd M. Riddick Pipe-in-Tree Farm Practicum," 1979, June 2-10 (album)
  - Cosmos Club, 1941-1990, (6 folders) (Box OS 9)
  - Cosmos Club, 1991-1996, undated, (3 folders) (Box OS 10)
  - Judicial Conference of D.C., 1980-1983, (4 folders) (Box OS 11)
  - Sigma Xi, 1974-1975, (3 folders)
  - Sigma Xi, 1976-1987, (6 folders) (Box OS 12)
  - Sigma Xi, 1987-1994, (4 folders) (Box OS 13)
  - U.S. Model Senate, 1966, 1974-1984, (4 folders)
  - U.S. Model Senate, 1985-1995, undated, (6 folders) (Box OS 14)
  - U.S. Senate Youth Program, 1979-1995, (4 folders) (Box OS 15)
  - Miscellaneous Organizations, 1974-1986, (3 folders)
- Printed Material Series, 1909-2000and undated
  Chiefly consists of programs and invitations to events in which Riddick participated; small directories of political and academic groups; clippings regarding Riddick or events of interest to him; Congressional publications, and published volumes regarding the history of the Capitol. Also includes a dissertation, The Discharge Petition: A Study of Congressional Politics, by Cedric Britt Beemer, dedicated to Riddick.
  - 1909-1974, (6 folders) (Box PM 1)
  - 1975-1991, (6 folders) (Box PM 2)
  - 1992-1994, (1 folder) (Box PM 3)
  - 1995-2000 and undated, (1 folder)
  - Clippings, 1940-1989and undated, (1 folder)
  - Clippings: Congressional Record, 1947-1987, (1 folder)
  - The Capitol: A Pictorial History, 1973, (volume)
  - The Capitol: A Pictorial History, 1981, (volume)
  - The Discharge Petition: A Study of Congressional Politics, 1975, (volume)
- Picture Series, 1937-1993and undated
  Contains photographs of United States senators, presidents, and other political figures as well as photographs of members of organizations of which Riddick was a member. Riddick is included in many of the pictures. Most photographs are black and white. Some are autographed.
  Arranged alphabetically by primary subject of the photograph.
  - A-E, 1941-1986and undated, (1 folder) (Box PS 1)
  - F-N, 1954-1994 and undated, (1 folder)
  - O-R, [1930s]-1989and undated, (1 folder)
  - S-Z and Miscellaneous, 1937-1993and undated, (1 folder)
- Miscellaneous Papers Series, 1914-2000and undated
  Consists of awards and tributes to Riddick, travel momentos, memorabilia, a motion picture film about congress, a transcript of an oral history of Riddick, and a few legal and financial papers.
  Arranged alphabetically by category with unclassified material at end of series.
  - Awards and Certificates, 1927-1991, (1 folder) (Box MP 1)
  - Biographical and Family Material, 1936-2000, (1 folder)
  - Financial Papers, 1935-1991, (1 folder)
  - Forest Dunes Condominium Property Owners Association, 1988-1997, (1 folder and 1 binder)
  - German Currency, 1914-1923, (1 folder)
  - Germany, Trip to, Diary,1937-1938, (1 folder)
  - Germany, Trip to, 1966, (1 folder)
  - Johannesburg, South Africa Trip, 1988, (1 folder)
  - Legal Papers, 1941-1990 and undated, (1 folder) (Box MP 2)
  - Oral History, 1980-1990, (1 folder)
  - Retirement Tributes, 1974-1975, (1 folder)
  - Scrapbook 1, 1973-1975and undated, (3 folders)
  - Scrapbook, Senate Procedure, 1958-1974and undated, (1 folder)
  - Speech by Lyndon Johnson,1965, (1 folder)
  - Interview with Mr. Truman, 1941 Nov. 27, (2pp)
  - Interview with Hiram Johnson, 1941 Aug. 13, (3pp)
  - Interview with Judge Leavy Wash, 1941 Aug. 6, (3pp)
  - Miscellaneous, 1908-1949, (1 folder)
  - Miscellaneous, 1950-2000 and undated, (5 folders) (Box MP 3)
  - Motion Picture Film: Congress in Action (Box MP 4)
- Oversize Material
  - Senate Activities, 1947-1987 and undated (bulk 1974-1985)
    - Voting Records, 1943 (Opaperfolder Folder 1)
  - Writings and Speeches, 1930-1992 and undated (bulk 1964-1981) (Opaperfolder Folder 1)
    - Resolutions, 1972 and 1974 (Opaperfolder Folder 1)
  - Picture Series, 1937-1993and undated
    - Atomic test sight, 1955 (Opaperfolder Folder 1)
    - Cosmos Club, 1983 (Opaperfolder Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Papers Series, 1914-2000and undated
    - Awards and Certificates, 1974-1997 (Opaperfolder Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Papers Series, 1914-1994 and undated
    - Scrapbook, 1927-1946 (Oversize-box 1)
- Accession (2007-0165), 1928-2000
  The addition (2007-0165) (50 items; 0.6 lin. ft.; 1928-2000) consists of Riddick's publications about parliamentary procedure; obituaries and other remembrances addressed to Riddick's wife upon his death; his high school diploma; and several VHS tapes, audiocassettes, and a mini-VHS cassette containing interviews and presentations by Riddick about his role as the Senate Parliamentarian.
  - Books
    - The United States Congress Organization and Procedure, 1949 (Box Acc. 07/165: Box 1)
    - Riddick's Rules of Procedure, 1985 (Box Acc. 07/165: Box 1)
    - Congress in Action: How a Bill Becomes a Law, 1948 (Box Acc. 07/165: Box 1)
  - Obituaries and remembrances, 2000 (Box Acc. 07/165: Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous clippings (unfoldered) (Box Acc. 07/165: Box 1)
  - Congressional Record, July 30, 1984 (Box Acc. 07/165: Box 1)
  - Majority and Minority Leaders of the Senate, April 1985 (Box Acc. 07/165: Box 1)
  - The Classification of United States Senators, 1966 (Box Acc. 07/165: Box 1)
  - Oral History transcript, 1990 (Box Acc. 07/165: Box 1)
  - VHS Cassettes
    - American Institute of Parliamentarians Williamsburg Practicums, 1994 (Box Acc. 07/165: Box 1)
    - The Library's commemoration of the 500,000th volume, April 1997
    - At the Williamsburg Practicum, June 1992
    - CSPAN Interview, May 1986
    - CSPAN Interview, October 1986
    - Speaking at Bob Jones University, October 1994
  - Audiocassettes
    - Oral History interview, June 13, 1990 (Box Acc. 07/165: Box 1)
    - Radio Interview in South Africa
    - American Institute of Parliamentarians: Riddick: Essence of Bylaws
  - Mini VHS
    - No title (TC-30 EHG tape) (Box Acc. 07/165: Box 1)
- Accession (2008-0179) 1933-1992
  The addition (2008-0179) (100 items; 0.6 lin. ft.; 1933-1993) contains publications, academic materials, clippings, correspondence, and miscellaneous materials, including a copy of the Senate Resolution 443 that declared Riddick as the Parliamentarian Emeritus of the U.S. Senate.
  This addition has been interfiled with Accession (2007-0165), Box 1.